Welcome back to AM Northwest. From a
five-foot narwhal horn to pottery from a
shipwreck here with fascinating pieces
from unique collections. We welcome back
antique appraiser Gary Gurmer. Great to
see you, Gary. >> Thank you for having
me, Helen. >> Okay, some unusual things
right here. Let's start with this
pottery. >> Yeah. Had a fellow call up
said he had some old pottery that he
inherited from his grandfather. And it's
this wonderful blue and white pottery
and it came from a shipwreck
uh off the coast of of Vietnam.
It was found in the late 1990s.
Uh and it was uh uh very famous. They
they brought these up. They found 250
pieces of this pottery that was being
shipped that when it sank. And these are
about 500 years old. All this blue and
white pottery. >> Oh wow. >> Yeah. And so
uh it's a the the call an
shipwreck. And on the bottom,
you'll see this is how smart I am. When
they brought it up, they inventoried
everything and they put the little tags
on it. All the really best pieces went
to museums, but then they had auctions
and sold off the rest. So, you'll find
these out there, but you they they you
should leave if you ever get one, leave
the sticker on it because that really
authenticates it. >> And you said you said
it was found in the 1990s. >> Yeah, the
shipwreck was found 500 years after it
sank. And yeah, it sank in the late
1400s. >> Yeah. And so let's say you you
you've have something like this in your
collection. Like how much is something
like this worth? Do you have any idea?
>> Yeah. You would think that being 500
years old, Chinese or or South uh Asian
pottery would be worth huge money, but
because there was so much from this
horde, you know, it's a supply and demand
thing. So these little pots are actually
bring more money than the bigger
pieces. Okay. >> These are little cosmetic
jars and perfume. And then of course
a little little trinket jar and everything
we have. So the shapes are used like
we do today. Um they're two to three
well they about $300 to $400. These are
$200 to $300 a piece. >> Now this is
fascinating. So tell me about this.
>> This is a little different estate
we're working on and it's a it's a narwhal
horn.
And um you know the narwhal is a big whale
fish whale type fish in the in the in
the Arctic Ocean. And this is actually
a tooth. It comes out of our the canine
tooth was from and it was in the dark
ocean. So this is they understand had a
lot of nerve endings in it. So it wasn't
just for hunting. It would test the
water water pressure and temperature.
I see. >> And kind of was helped it
understand where it was at and could
relate to other animals. They did use it
for hunting to stun other animals and
they would communicate by knocking their
horns >> their horns together. >> Together.
>> Wow. So but this is essentially
ivory. >> It is. >> So you can't really
sell this, right? Well, yes and no. I
don't know yet. >> Okay. >> Um, no, they
can't hunt it. The native people, the
Inuit people can, but uh uh we
can't, right? But and so it is it is
highly restricted, although they're not
highly endangered. >> Um, interesting.
They're uh but it is highly restricted.
So, it has to be before a certain date
and you have to have paperwork to back
up where it's from and how old it is,
whether you can sell it. And I just
got this estate we're working on and I
haven't gone through the paperwork
yet. So, don't call the police just yet
behind it. Yeah, there's a story behind
this. >> Like, how does someone get in
get a hold of something like that? >>
Well, the that's one of the unfortunate
parts of my job is that I usually meet
people after they've died, >> right?
>> And so, I didn't get the full story
on how he found it. Like I said, we just
got it. I I was so excited I had to
come share it, right? >> Um, and so
hopefully he has do more documentation
on where it came from and what how he got
it. Uh, the problem is now also selling
anything like that that's made of ivory.
uh even if it's before the time it's
legal, you have all the paperwork to show,
there are no platforms to sell it on.
None of >> No one wants to buy that.
>> No. Well, no one everyone wants to
buy it. It's none of them want to be the
conduit like eBay and those places cuz
they don't want to have to sit there and
fight the government on each and every
piece. >> I gota Okay, let's take a look
at this incredible pottery. I love the
shine to it. >> Isn't it wonderful?
>> Yeah. And are they all different
types? Like >> Yeah, they're different
glazes. These were made by a very famous
artist named Beatatrice Woods and she
was kind of uh a California artist. Um
and very famous. She's one of the main
people. She was known as the mama of
dada. She brought the the Dada movement to
the US from Europe and then she settled
outside Los Angeles up in the mountains
and and studied pottery. And >> these
are different kind of glazes. This is
called a volcanic type glaze. And actually
the Natlers perfect perfected it, but
she used it too where when it's hot they
rub it with their hands with you, you
know, asbestous gloves and pop anything
to give it that rough kind of look.
>> That's amazing. >> But she perfected
this gold iridescent one. >> That's my
favorite. >> Yeah, she perfected that.
And look >> and you you've got a So she
signed it Bo E A T O. So but
that was for Beatatric Woods.
And uh yeah, that that metallic looking
glaze that she figured out how to do it
so that the uh metal dust in the
glaze would uh expand and be at the
top of the of the surface. So it would
be iridescent like it has a metal on it.
>> How much would something like this?
>> About 5,000 for this one. >> Wow.
Okay. >> 56,000. And these are about four
4,000 because the gold is what really
everyone wants all of it, but this is
the one. This is probably about 4,000.
That one's 3500 range. And you can't
put these in the dishwasher. >> No, they
don't go in the dishwasher. It was funny,
the estate I was working on with that,
they had them sitting in the corner and
we're going through all the mother's art
and stuff and they had them just piled
there and I ran and got >> those cloth
napkins and put between them so that
they were >> they wouldn't hit each other
>> and they didn't the family didn't know
what they had. I said, "Well, you have
with these 14 pieces you
have you have about 80$90,000
right there." >> Oh my gosh. >> And I
said, "So don't eat your Cheerios out of
those." >> Oh my gosh. Isn't that
incredible? But that whole movement was about
um turning everyday objects into art.
I mean this was never meant to be used
other than to look at. I mean you didn't
like put anything in them but it was to
it was uh different forms to show
off different kinds of experimental
>> actually see that like you can say
this is just a piece of beauty, a piece of
art. >> Absolutely. It is. I think it's
wonderful and I just it's the fun part
of my job is I never know exactly what
we're going to find in someone's home.
Yeah. And you wouldn't be able to tell a
price on the horn. >> Well, if if if it
was sell if we can and I'm assuming it
was cuz the fellow it came from, Neil,
was very methodical about everything he
did. Um, and I'm sure I just had I just
got literally got it this last week and
I haven't gone through the paperwork
yet. >> Uh, selling it. It's about 2,000
to $3,000. >> Wow. >> In that range if
we can find one. >> Incredible.
You have some really interesting pieces,
Gary Gurmer. Thank you very much. Good
to see you. Please, please do not move
this table fast, okay? Just keep it
slow. We don't want anything to break.
All right,